# 其实要吃就要吃这种
This is what we like
# 纯手工的
100% hand-made
# 一个四川人
As a local from Sichuan
# 从小吃到大的绝对正宗
I grew up with this dish
# 冰粉
The Ice Jelly
# 杨兵
Chef Bing Yang
# 师父好
Hello master
# 好久没有看到你了
Long time no see!
# 好久没有看到师父了
Indeed.
# 今天给我们做个啥子菜嘞
What are you cooking today?
# 今天我做一个冰粉
I am making the ice jelly
# 冰粉
Ice jelly!
# 安逸
Nice!
# 说到这个冰粉
Speaking of the ice jelly
# 可能谁都在做
Many are making it
# 那么我今天
So today
# 真正的做一个四川人
As a real local from Sichuan
# 真的
I will share the authentic
# 冰粉
Ice jelly
# 绝对正宗 从小吃到大的
That I grew up with
# 好 开始
OK, let's go
# 这个是冰粉籽
This is the "Ice jelly seeds"
# 这个东西其实在四川
In Sichuan
# 可以这么说
This plant is very common
# 满大街都是
Everyone on the streets
# 满山上到处都是
and the mountains
# 四川话叫(假)酸浆籽
The plant is called "apple of Peru" (Nicandra physalodes)
# 它长的形状啊
It looks like
# 跟东北的菇娘一样
golden berries
# 一模一样的形状
Almost the same
# 然后把它掰开之后
You break the fruit open
# 把籽取出来
to collect the seeds
# 它的果胶含量非常的(高)
The seeds are rich in fruit gel
# 这是一种植物
So it is a plant
# 对
Yes
# 这是一种植物
The seeds of a specific plant
# 其实这个东西在网上随处可以买得到的
But of course you can easily buy it online
# 它在冰粉里面起啥子作用
So what are they used for?
# 它的果胶含量重
It is rich in fruit gel
# 就是能把水凝结在一起
Which binds water together
# 我是用的是50克
I am using 50 grams
# 这个是100克
We have 100 grams here
# 分成两份
So let's divide it by half
# 稍微洗一下就行
Give it a quick wash
# 不要洗久了
Not too much
# 因为我是做的是两个颜色的
I am making two versions, with different colors
# 然后两个盆 一样放一个
Now we need two bowls, one for each.
# 最好其实是井水 井水安逸
It would be the best if we use mineral water from the well.
# 对
Indeed
# 50克
50 grams
# 放矿泉水
Mineral water
# 3斤半到4斤左右的水就可以了
we need about 1.5-4 kg of water
# 这个好 差不多了
Something like that
# 然后这个也是一样
Same here
# 咱们做两种今天
We are making two versions
# 泡一下
Let the seeds soak
# 大概可能是泡个五六分钟
for about 5-6 mins
# 因为它果胶含量比较重的话
Because of the fruit gels in the seeds
# 你稍微用水
You need to soak it with water
# 把它泡的时候泡一下的话
If you soak it
# 发得快一点
It absorbs water more quickly
# 那么现在还来一个
Then we have this
# 这个很有不一样的东西
Somehting sepcial
# 红糖
Brown sugar
# 他在四川叫砂糖
We call them “rock sugar" in Sichuan
# 它形状很像砂块
because it looks like rocks
# 你看
look
# 如果你在超市里面
if you buy it from the supermarket
# 或者在北方买的红糖
or the brown sugar in northern China
# 它是粉状的
It's usually in podwers
# 要不就是块状的 片状的
or in slices
# 然后其实我掰了一个角
This is only a corner of the whole piece
# 很大一块 用这个刀这样
Slice it like this
# 四川的红糖的话
The brown sugar in Sichuan
# 它比较香
It has a better aroma
# 因为普通红糖话
while the regular ones
# 它出来的红糖水是黄的
has a yellow-ish color
# 而且它香味口感 焦糖味不够
and the flavour is not strong enough
# 焦糖味不够
Especially the caramel flavour
# 四川的红糖比较纯
The brown sugar from Sichuan is purer
# 然后一般好多人就是熬
Many tend to boil it
# 但是我是拿着蒸
I prefer to steam
# 因为熬的时候
When you boil it
# 如果稍微掌握不好的话
If you are not experienced
# 它容易会糊掉
It might burn
# 焦糖就糊掉
The caramel may burn
# 会发苦
and get bitter
# 这是一斤的红糖
Here's 500g of sugar
# 配上二两水
with 100g water
# 好了
OK
# 马上就化去了
It dissolves easily
# 巴适得很
Nice
# 巴适
# 放蒸锅 蒸一下一般情况下
Place it in the steamer and
# 一般情况下蒸个10分钟左右就可以了
usually it takes about 10 mins
# 差不多泡了有几分钟了
We have soaked them for a few minutes
# 我拿一盆里面搁点果肉
Let me put some pitaya in it
# 对
right
# 差不多的量
something like this
# 我大概可能搁了有个100克嘛
about 100 grams
# 红的火龙果
red pitaya fruits
# 我这个先放着
Let it sit there
# 我现在搓这个
Now let's rub these seeds
# 这个泡了
after soaking
# 你看它里面开始起坨坨了
the seeds start to lump up
# 师父你看里面结块了
See the lumps there?
# 这个时候其实搓冰粉
There are tricks
# 其实还有一些讲究
in rubbing the seeds
# 如果说咱们在水底下去搓
If we do it under water
# 出来是没气泡亮的
There's no air bubbles and it's transparant
# 但是现在我们基本上
But what we do now
# 小时候还有现在不管这些商家
also the shops do it when I was a kid, but not anymore
# 咱们都是
We do it
# 是这样
like this
# 从水上去搓
over the water
# 待会儿满盆的都是气泡
Then there will be a lot of air bubbles
# 气泡一个是它有口感
the bubbles improves the texture
# 再一个是好看
and also it looks better
# 其实在四川
In Sichuan
# 不管大街小巷
on the streets and the little alleys
# 学校门口还有码头
outside school or at the pier
# 然后到处都有来一个大姐或者这个老太太
there are always someone
# 她就卖冰粉
selling this ice jelly
# 对然后好了
Ok
# 这稍微再搓一下
give it a bit more rubbing
# 包括这个也是稍微给它再搓一下
this one too
# 因为今天做的是两个口味
this one has a different flavor
# 对
right
# 幺妹儿买啥子来 买冰粉儿
"what are you selling? ice jelly!"
# 这个时候特别关键的一个东西
This is important
# 石灰5克
5 grams of lime powder
# 然后现在把水先放进去
then we add some water
# 放半斤水
about 250 grams
# 其实在买冰粉的时候
when you buy the ingredients
# 他就给你带这个石灰
it often comes with the slaked lime powder
# 泡上
let is soak
# 放一边不用管它
and let it there
# 石灰是含的碳酸钙嘛
there are Calcium carbonate in the powder (此处存疑，因为前面说用的是熟石灰，那么应该是氢氧化钙，且碳酸钙并不可溶)
# 加了石灰水之后啊
once you add the slaked lime water
# 他就把那些一些比较发散的果胶
it will bind the fruit gels
# 跟水完全融合在一起
with the water molecules
# 才能有果冻的感觉
to form a jelly
# 混为一体
togehter
# 搓的时候
when we rub the seeds
# 其实就让他果胶充分得出来
we want to extract the fruit gels as much as possible
# 大概其实搓个几分钟就可以了
we need to rub it for a few minutes
# 黏了 对了
right, it gets sticky now
# 黏了特别黏起泡了
sticky, and there are bubbles
# 对
right
# 离开水这么挤
press it over the water
# 然后泡沫就丰富嗯
to form all the air bubbles
# 待会做出来冰粉里面
they will stay in the
# 全是泡沫
ice jelly
# 非常漂亮
very nice
# 直到搓到纱布袋里面
rub until it is not that sticky anymore
# 没有那么粘稠了
in the bag
# 其实差不多了
it's almost done
# 好了
alright
# 现在加一个石灰水
now the slaked lime water
# 沉淀不用管它
only use the supernatant
# 尽量的朝一个方向打它
stir in one direction
# 然后慢加快搅
and gradually speed up
# 使这个水微微的发黄
until it turns a little bit yellow-ish
# 就可以
then it's done
# 诶 颜色变了
it's changing color
# 黄了 就变化了
yes turning yellow
# 这个不能加的太多
don't put too much
# 大概就是咱们3斤多加四两左右就可以了
we have about 200 grams in 1.5 kg
# 这个就让他静置在这放一下
let it rest here
# 放冰箱先静置一下
and let it rest in the fridge
# 好
OK
# 放冰箱
In the fridge
# 现在来搓这个
now let's take care of this
# 带果肉的
with the fruits
# 今天放的是火龙果
we are using piyata
# 顺便搓的时候
so also rub on the fruits
# 一边去拿去捏捏果肉
when rubbing the seeds
# 然后夏天的话
in the summer
# 加西瓜也好
It's also nice to use watermelon
# 或者加火龙果也好
instead of pitaya
# 各种颜色哪个味道出来都非常的好
both will be nice in color and taste
# 小手洗真白啊
your hands are so clean
# 搓冰粉儿之前
before doing this
# 一定把手洗干净了
always wash your hands clean
# 对 要洗安逸 洗白了
right
# 其实要吃就要吃这种
the best is made
# 纯手工的
100% by hand
# 或者说你带个胶皮手套
if you wear a pair of gloves
# 没有手感
then you cannot feel the ingredients
# 还要去感觉一下手感噢噢
you have to feel it
# 老规矩对慢下快搅
pour slowly, stir quickly
# 朝一个方向去搅
in one direction
# 不要下面的沉淀
don't pour any of the sediments in
# 只要上面澄清的的水
only the supaernatent
# 好了
OK
# 哦了
Nice
# 好了
# 这就差不多了
that's about it
# 这就差不多
right
# 因为放一下冰箱的话
it will taste better
# 口感会更好
after resting in the fridge
# 特别漂亮
looks beautuful
# 这个刚取出来先舀这个吧
Let's begin with this
# 让他带点眼儿
leave some space in here
# 本身他里面就有点水分
it contains a lot of moisture
# 因为待会要放糖
and we are going to put sugars in
# 水分不能太多
we don't want it to be too waterly
# 你看这里面特别漂亮
beautiful, look
# 带气孔对
all the air bubbles
# 晶莹剔透
very jiggly
# 一看就爽快的
looks great
# 这样就差不多了
that's enough
# 特别好
nice
# 擓的时候啊弄成片这么下
scoop the into slicec
# 好看
beautiful
# 起丝了 拉黏
look how thick it is
# 就是5:1的
the ratio is 5:1
# 再拉一遍
do it agian
# 稠了也不行 稀了也不行
the thickness has to be perfect
# 就要这样
like this
# 刚好拉丝
to form a thick stream
# 红糖
sugar
# 来一勺
one scoop
# 你师父爱吃甜的多来点
Da Ye loves it, let's give him a bit more
# 再来一个
one more
# 不管它有没有水果
Regardless of the fruits
# 红糖是少不了的
You have to have the sugar
# 山楂微微带一点酸
hawthorn is a little bit sour
# 山楂粒儿对买点山楂粒儿
right
# 花生碎
peanuts
# 必须的
that's a must
# 花生碎
crushed peanuts
# 葡萄干 葡萄干是经典
raisins are classic, too
# 你的水果要换成榴莲的好吃了
Imagine replacing the fruits with durian
# 可以各种口味都可以的
You can make it into any flavors
# 我就不喜欢那臭味
I don't like durian
# 来一个必须要加的一个东西
Now, another must-have
# 有了这个东西它是点睛之笔
The most important trick
# 醪糟
Lao Zao
# 醪糟是魂
That's the soul of this dish
# 其实这个小吃它非常简单
See, this is actually very simple
# 家家户户都会做
everyone can make it
# 拿了一个薄荷叶
a piece of mint
# 好勒 好看
look
# 和匀了
mix it well
# 别洒
don't spill it!
# 嚯
wow
# 太好吃了
amazing!
# 原汁原味原生态
original flavour, original taste
# 对 而且还是本地人
made by a local chef
# 而且营养健康
nutritious and healthy
# 你看到没有
see?
# 你看红糖
look at the brown sugar
# 你看人家有的熬
some boil it
# 你看人家就是隔水蒸
we steamed it
# 我特别喜欢
I love it
# 这带火龙果
this one is with pitaya
# 火龙果
pitaya
# 颜色五颜六色
beautiful mixture of colors
# 颜色鲜艳
lovely
# 我不吃
I don't need to taste it
# 我一看这我心里就喜欢
to know that I would love it, just by looking at it
# 安逸
lovely
# 这里边带着他的情感
it's made with love
# 对
correct
# 你看从小背个背篓
when you were a kid
# 喂猪的猪草
on your way to feed the pigs
# 然后我们摘几个果子
pick some fruits on the way
# 回家自己做
and go back home to make this dish
# 你看从背着果子
You came along
# 走到今天
all the way
# 成长为这个行业里边的
to become a master chef
# 大厨
in this industry
# 佼佼者
One of the best
# 杨大厨
Chef Yang
# 巴适得很
Nice!
# 师父的面前永远不可能当大厨
I'm never a master chef in front of you.
# 尽量在这两天
(how long can I keep my spring onion oil)
preferably use it within 2 days
# 或者三天
or 3 days
# 连续就（把它）用完了
use it up.
# 网友问说
Follows ask:
# 做好的葱油
how long can I keep
# 能够保存多久
my spring onion oil
# 这是个大问题是吧
that's a problem
# 你像家里炸个花椒油
when you prepare a Sichuan pepper oil
# 比如做打卤面
for the noodles
# （放）到那卤上面特别香
it smells amazing
# 实际上葱油也是一样
Same with the spring onion oil
# 我们就用多少
Plan for it
# 比如我这周有两天在家休息
say, I'm staying at home for two days
# 必须要在家要做饭
and I am cooking at home
# 你第一次炸葱油的时候
then, when you make the iol
# 可以多炸一点
you can prepare for the use of 2 days
# 尽量在这两天或者三天
and preferably, finish it within 2 days
# 连续就把用完了
use it up
# 千万别说
Never be like:
# 我炸了一盆葱油
I spend all the efforts
# 下了那么多料
with all the ingredients
# 我下礼拜还得用
I want to keep some for next week too.
# 再下礼拜它肯定不香了
It's not going to smell as good
# 一定要现（炸）现用为好
The best is to prepare it when you need it
# 保存几天
and keep it only for a few days
# 两三天 不宜炸得太多
2-3 days max. Don't make too much in one batch.
# 你看我们
It's like
# 到涮羊肉馆里边吃饭
going to the hotpot
# 人家现给咱们炸的辣椒油
If they serve the freshly made chilli oil
# 老远就闻着就特香
You can smell it from distance
# 但是说他要给你拿了一个陈的
but if they serve you an old one
# 辣椒油
stored chilli oil
# 什么味儿也没有
you would smell nothing
# 只有辣味 没有辣椒的香味
it only tastes spicy, but there's no aroma
# 这个道理是一样
Same here
# 另外我们炸完葱油
Also, when you make your own spring onion oil
# 一定要有个盖
store it with a cover
# 要封着它
to seal it
# 或者保鲜膜给它封上
or use a film to seal it
# 不能让这个味儿
you have to prevent the aroma
# 全给跑出来
from running out
# 是吧
right?
# 所以要有个瓶
Get a bottle
# 有个罐
or a jar
# 一定要把它封起来
and seal it
# 能保住它的香味
to keep the aroma